[Music]
you say think is gonna happen hoping
that they don't happen hoping that by
virtue of saying and it's like a spell
and then it doesn't happen that what's
happening
well actually in our first conversation
you said something that gave me the
shivers he said like you said like what
happens if a million people are you know
died and we have to watch that and what
would the culture do he said something
like that and that was like like a month
before this whole business came down and
I remember when you said that I you know
people say stuff and you don't you just
you just it just washes over you most of
the time but that kind of made me shiver
a little bit I remember that moment that
to him I'm releasing the the one heaven
dialogue that three of us had tomorrow
on my channel so cool cool great yeah
well maybe we can we can delve in deeper
with the subject with the subjects that
we've already started to discuss you
know we are talking about we've already
started talking we talking about kovat
and we've already started talking about
how this is a strange time a weird time
a bizarre time and and and the time
actually time itself is sort of
different during this period and which
is the Greek word Kairos that was my
first question that I had for you guys
is is if you could collaborate on this
this Kairos this idea of critical moment
sure you might I go for a second so is
what's important to that I put some
fighting into that before all of this
when because in my series because I
originally got the notion from Tillich
and in
he talks about it in quite a bit of his
work and also connection you know it
took the courage to be and which he's
dealing with the meeting crisis and the
effect it's having on religion and his
time and of course it's he gets it he
has the Christian slant on it because
he's a Protestant theologian but and he
claims that it was that there was a
really interesting sort of Christian
spin on the Greek term one of the
original metaphor is not metaphorical
mythological in the good sense of myth
is the idea that of christ's advent came
in the fullness of time so the idea is
that systems will go along in place and
they have a lot of inertia to them
they're very resistant to change and
then certain sets of conditions will
console 8 such that an intervention will
have a huge has a huge potential to
really steer the course of things so the
idea about a Kairos is a fullness of
time in which timing matters because it
can turn the way in which time unfolds
so there's there's sort of many things
but that we're only in potentia have
come to a place where actualization and
transformation is possible and and so
the way I try to take that mythological
notion that mythological existential
notion because you you know you can note
you can note that in your own life you
do not like when you've been in a
relationship with person and you can
come to a point where you feel that you
know the relationship has been stable
and then it hits this point right it
hits this point and you go oh you know
this you know people talk about maker
breakpoints in in relationships and so
you get a sense that oh this this could
change the whole course of nature of the
relationship so there's that
mythological sense there's that personal
phenomenological sense and then I think
it I try to map it onto dynamical
systems and the idea of criticality in
self-organizing systems this comes from
per Bach systems are self-organizing in
the
quite stable and then they get to a
point where the processes the very
processes that made them stable actually
start to undermine their structure the
classic example is the grain of you know
the column of stand that's falling and
it builds a mound and the mound is
stable for long periods and then when it
gets too high because of its
self-organization it goes critical it
avalanches its structure breaks down and
that criticality can either lead to the
disintegration of the system or it can
afford a new base from which something
new can emerge and be restructured and
so in my mind I sort of put those three
together when I think about Kairos and I
think we're getting increasing evidence
that we're in something I mean I think a
lot of stuff is already chaotic and then
I think the the the Cova crisis has just
been an accelerant of of the Kairos
Blair I yeah I mean I hold it similarly
I first got it actually from off table
Omar who was at Meridian University
whose students of James Helens work and
then read it read Hillman writing about
Kairos and relating it to this notion of
opportunity in particular and this is
kind of like penetrable opening within
the usually impenetrable fabric of fate
or time that there's like a nick in time
like in the nick of time in the sense if
there's a chink in the armor of Chronos
so that you can get in somehow and then
so there's something about it too and
relating it to the complex systems is
something that I do instinctively in the
in the realm of like individual
development that if you look at critical
periods in the development of any
individual the critical period of
adolescent identity formation for
example like most of adolescence feels
chyron ik it feels so much pregnant
opportunity so much can go right or
wrong and so much is locking in even
physiological the dysregulation andrey
regulation of whole parts of identity
structure but also
hormones and growth spurts and other
things similarly in early childhood when
you've got these critical the so called
critical periods which are not set in
stone but you can feel them when they're
happening as an educator or a parent and
they're kind of written into the way the
system develops and grows so similar
then you have a system that's growing
like embryologically for example or
developmentally epigenetically within
childhood
you're giving these periods of real dis
equilibration adolescence is a great
example where there's to be expected a
kind of identity dysregulation affective
dysregulation these things are kind of
par for the course there because the
system's trying to get up and into some
new form of patterning so crises are
usually moments of opportunity
they're usually these moments of Kairos
and identity crises in particular when
you're thinking about the individual and
the kind of phenomenology of Kairos in
your own life like what's it like what
does it feel like you can remember those
periods in your life when it just ended
and so the question of kind of antigen
ontogeny recapitulates phylogeny to what
extent we can apply that model to the
growth of cultures and civilizations we
could say something like you know the
civilization is in a kind of adolescent
identity crisis of mmm neurotic import
which is to say like this if we become a
planetary civilization this kind of
pandemic is something we're gonna have
to be able to deal with because of the
nature of Trade and the nature of the
travel and the nature of their
organization structures it's kind of
like this is much like to be a mature
species that has planet eyes like grow
up we need to figure out how to deal
with this and so that's this moment of
opportunity where either the adolescent
feels with reality or the adolescent
adapts to miss adapts to reality and
create some identity structure and
behavior patterns that are actually
maladaptive and then you've locked in a
kind of a difficult way forward into
full maturation if not an end up being
self terminating identity construction
mmm-hmm so that's one way I kind of
model it I don't know if it's useful to
think about it that way
you know there are limitations to it but
there's something powerful to yeah you
said that just you said that it's either
or either you go into a new higher level
of realization or the thing
disintegrates and when I was saying that
I think both kind of happens
simultaneously right it depends I mean
isn't that what sort of what's happening
now or what could be happening now or
well I mean it's may be that there's
there's a degree of the criticality
means the previous structure is
disintegrating literally to some degree
so but there is there's a there's a
tipping point right where if you go too
far the disintegration the entropy
overtakes the system and the system
collapses right and and and and you
might you might and and then it gets in
it can get stuck into a aberrant pattern
which is kind of like I think with
Jacques is talking about with the waking
goal become maladaptive you know like a
team you know who you know gets into
crime or something like that nothing
like that but there's a way there's a I
want to riff on with Jacques said
because so when you look at that those
that self-organizing criticality you can
actually see it in the brain you can
actually see it at work in the insight
like this is the work of stuff and in
Dixon in fact if when people are locked
into a frame and this is why maybe
bringing in framing might help because
we could sort of link framing an
identity that might give us even a
richer metaphor because they get locked
into a particular frame and then what
you have to do is you actually have to
you have to throw a lot of noise you
have to destabilize them you have to
introduce entropy into the system and
then that will actually provoke an
insight and what's interesting is you
can see development I mean I think you
did make a good argument
if from interpreting Piaget because he
sees the stages as bound to
systematicity of error you could see
development when you move from one stage
to another a systematic insight not just
an insight here or here but a much more
comprehensive set of insights like so
that your entire ways of looking at the
world entire ways of being would be
changing and that's where you could be
even see the cognitive change and the a
change in identity are then start to be
woven together and and why why that
might be helpful to think about it is we
sort of officially in terms of the text
books we're not we're not supposed to
call them critical periods anymore was
for because because the turn out the
term had that you know the you know if
you know if you're not exposed to
language by the time you're 12
you'll never get syntax and it had that
sort of so the the terminology doesn't
matter but it's felicitous here because
we now call them sensitive periods and
so the idea here is just like the noise
can sensitize the system and make it
possible for it insight and if you look
at complex systems you have sensitive
dependence on initial conditions when
you get into these Kairos States actions
that normally that would have just been
submerged into the system have like they
have a tremendous capacity the sense to
change the future course of the entire
system mmm and and so why I'm bringing
that up story this is a little bit
belated I'm trying to get the cognitive
and the the development of identity
linked to this notion of a special kind
of sensitivity because what that then
brings in that is that there's a timing
issue to this right there's a timing
issue to this
that's really really crucial so like an
action that would it have been impotent
four weeks five weeks ago yeah right now
might make a big difference and it might
also be impotent from five weeks from
now right we're in we're in a period
where this
system is sensitive to our actions and
if we can figure out a system ax tissa T
in the air this is how I'm trying to
bring it all together we can make an
intervention that can permeate
promulgate throughout that entire
systematicity so it seems like if I
could just jump in that what we do right
now is very important yeah it's what we
do right now is very important but we
have to couple that to a deep kind of
discernment we have to try and track out
like is it in all of the chaos and all
of the noise is there a systematicity of
error signal we're getting error signals
this went wrong this went wrong this
went wrong this was wrong they give up
the kid is trapped in conservation
errors they're making they're giving us
all kinds of error signals and then
something happens in their cognition
where their brain figures out oh wait
these errors are all related if I start
doing this from now on I won't make any
of these mistakes again we could do
something analogous we have to bring in
there has to be like we have to find
that systematicity in the error we have
to find where we could do so we can find
like a nexus point right so we can we
can we can find what's it sensitive to
and where's the nexus point and where
can our actions make the most impact
right now so it's a timing it's a timing
it's a sensitivity issue it's an issue
but trying to find the systematicity in
the error I think the people like we've
got a we've got a shift off of it's just
chaos we've got a shift - okay yes
there's lots of noise there's lots of
entropy let's try and find because if
there's no systematicity - very well
we're screwed
yeah there's no systematicity error our
interventions won't make a systematic
difference and the system just gonna
everything's just going to collapse
right and so it's it's a timing issue
it's the sensitivity issue and most
importantly it's a discernment issue
we've got to do a lot of work to try and
figure out what do what what what what
Gestalt what Consulate's
all these error signals so that we get
some kind of unified sense of how we can
make use of the carros that's what I'm
trying to argue for
so I'm at me let's did that make I did I
think it did um Zach
maybe Zach could riff on on this notion
of what we work how we can make use of
this Kairos because that seems to be the
question right is and you know what John
speaking to is exactly correct from my
perspective of thinking about
development and learning like if you're
in a class and during the entire class
you get through you're never confused
and you're right like a perfect paper at
the end you have not learned anything
right yeah well you I've always tell my
students like I want you to be very
confused at certain points and that
confusion is like it's kind of Kairos
because you thought you understood and
now you've encountered something and how
you don't understand so you've been what
Piaget says disequilibrium right the
ability for you to just like run with it
is it no longer viable you have to
somehow adjust your operating and so if
you're in a situation you're trying to
develop or learn you need to be
comfortable with being disick wa
liberated thrown off and put in this
chaotic confusion and then as Johnny
Sack I was not saying within that you
need to then start looking for the
invariants because I'm going you're
hunting that's what Piaget was always
looking for the the abstraction of
invariants from from the environment and
first you discover the environment with
your son the invariants with your
sensory motor properties and affordances
of the body and then slowly you
extracting Berens from the social and
the physical into these abstractions and
then into principles and paradigms
processes and things so there's
something here there's an opportunity
for the social system itself to move
into a kind of higher order of
abstraction and complexity being able to
look at what's actually invariant
because when the simulation is going
it's not quite clear to tell what's real
and what's not real where's the
invariance like it's all working so when
you're perfectly aquila braiding your
class and economics so it's making
perfect sense there's a good opportunity
that you're missing
part of economics precisely because it's
working but there's something wrong
there's something missing there it's
working so well that you can tell
something's wrong it's working so you
can't and so this is what's been
happening with the civilization for a
long time it's been working so well for
the key members of the whole nation
yeah yeah yep enough error signal it can
absorb it it's so powerful
exactly so it's absorbing their signal
and so now there's this thing where are
now we're getting a sense of all the
possible error signals and now is John
saying we can look at the system today
the error systematicity of the errors
and detect the invariance and the mass
the opportunity to move to a higher
order of abstraction spelled reflective
abstraction in the pisciadood model and
then you have the grasp of consciousness
with the company's own so that's the
inside which is we put it in front of
you the subject becomes object as Keegan
says and then the grasp of consciousness
comes in there's insight and then you
can consolidate at the higher level
hopefully is that's the other thing you
can have the insight and then drop back
down and this is Kurt Fisher is great
instead like this movement about this
zone of proximal development the
development to a range is such that you
can pop up and see it and then drop back
down let me hop up and see it again drop
back down so it's not just eating the
inside it's also finding the ways to get
the scaffolding in place to secure the
inside now kind of moving forward and
that's the level consolidation and so
then there's this notion of enduring and
transitional structures as part of the
developmental process that there are
some structures which are transient
they're put in place temporarily to get
to a structure that's actually an
enduring structure part of the learning
process like different kind of steps
that you can use you can have parts of
the web as fisher described it that's it
yeah what structures are enduring and
what structures are sort of superficial
and are just treads transition
structures right and this is the deep
question and development you know like
there are some structures you don't
discard like the principles of
mathematics that you got from sensory
motor operation
those are partier and during cognitive
structures but lower levels of moral
development often you do kind of discard
or at least you put them in a different
kind of context so yeah there's there's
many strands here but I pick up my
general yeah please so one is to let's
so what you just said was very helpful
because it helps me try to refine this
discernment that I'm trying to put up
because part of like let's go back to
the insight problem-solving and one of
the things you do to get people to
afford insight as you call it you do the
notice and variance heuristic you get
people to pay attention and this is
where why humility is really important
but you get people to pay attention to
failed problem formulations and then you
try to notice what's invariant across
those problem formulations and then you
change that and that's exactly how you
afford insight so this this brings up a
sort of a question in my mind it's more
of a challenge to discernment which is
how do you you have to you have to you
know you have to notice the good
invariance that you're gonna track as
you're talking about exact but you also
have to notice the bad invariance that
you have to let go of but you have to
abandon in order to get the insight that
is needed for the transformation does
that make they're sort of part of the
wisdom is what's the so you get the
noise we turn it into systematicity as
you said we're looking for the
invariance but I think there's even
something more fine-grain we have to be
able to discern the good invariance if
you'll allow me these normative terms
from the bad invariance the bad
invariants like that might be you know
analogous to you know the sets of
constraints in the child schema you know
that was actually holding them back and
they have to be relaxed but as you said
that doesn't mean you abandon all
invariance because that's a disaster and
so it's not just it's not sorry I'm not
I'm not trying to be critical or exact
I'm trying to build on it it's not just
sort of finding the invariance it's also
finding it's also distinguishing between
the two kinds of invariants and getting
the right trade-off between them I think
it's part of what we're also what I'm
also trying to get to with your help to
this notion of discernment that we need
to bring in did does that make sense
it does makes perfect sense
and it's interesting that kind of
emotion and cognition are completely
inter digitated and union model and so
you get although those works mostly are
not translated so he's conceived as a
cognitive but it always says that
feeling emotion and cognition they're
related and so there's a there's the the
discernments not just cognitive cuz
you're right there's a lot I mean
there's a lot of invariants that we
don't own you know because it's not
relevant right because it's not part of
the of the field of what matters to the
developing child and so this is where
again I think our identity and cognition
are related as well because eventually
what matters to me is a function of who
I take myself to be and so in that sense
this question of who one is and how one
feels which is to say how one uses
emotion as an information system those
are kind of like more foundational than
the cognitive moment not more
foundational but there's a very deep
interaction between these and you can
you cannot remove and this is what makes
AI so dangerous right is that if you're
removing the affective and embodied
vector of salience and relevance let's
say then your unmoored
from what actually matters and this is
that difference between the simulation
and the reality that civilizations going
to Sue's that if you're if the commodity
disguises its relation to the actual
biosphere so you don't realize that
actually this thing
it's the disembodied idea but the it's
actual body is quite dangerous
completely unsustainable couldn't be
extracted at that rate for another two
years five years you know depending on
what the commodity is and so there's
this way that though the cognitive
apparatus needs to be within the the
affective and the evaluative and I think
embodied contain
when that helps get the sense of which
invariance am i detecting right I agree
with that
I mean fact I think that's fundamental
to relevance realization Montagu
actually talked about you know the
difference between us and computers to
use your your point azar is that we have
to take care of ourselves and then
therefore we have to care about
information and so I'm using care here
in a Heidegger sense that what we're
taught as relevance realization is
ultimately and I think this will get us
back to the affective stuff even the
existential stuff the the you know like
you're talking about the level of
identity because relevance realization
is also ultimately processed by which
you're committing it's it's it is acts
of commitment and they could be micro
acts of committing no seconds of
attention seconds of arousal but it can
also be macro acts where you can you're
committing long periods of your very
precious and limited attention cognitive
resources time I so I I I think that
ultimately and this is what we don't
have to do the a I think but this is one
of the things holding back AI right now
because because ultimately relevance
realization is never cold calculation
it's never cold calculation it's always
an act of commitment and now I'm gonna
sound like howdy there and commitment is
always an act of caring and commitment
and caring are always identity forming
processes that's just the way I mean the
best way to find out who I am is not to
do some sort of romantic introspective
act it's to pay careful attention to
what I systematically care about that's
that that's that that's a clearer way of
getting at Who I am
and what do I commit to what what can
you rely ibly hold me to committing to
well Jonathan Jonathan will commit to
this well that's the kind of person John
is and so I think I think that if we
could if we could agree that you know
this process we're talking about is
deeply one of caring and commitment and
cognition and I think that overlaps with
your terms of effect and identity really
deeply then is it possible and I like
your point that it's only that fully
embodied process
that can get the discernment or at least
get good discernment between the bad
environments and the good invariants
what's the analog for the culture right
because I think you're right if we're
taking a look at an individual cognition
we can you know there's relevance
realization it's never cold calculation
it's you know it's about trying to zero
in on what I should care about what I
should commit to what I there by
identify with right and that that whole
process is you know and insight is just
moments where that's restructuring and
and that's what actually is helping me
pull apart the grid and variance from
the batted variance within times of
development times of Kairos so Zach this
is a hard question but I'm loving it
over to you what's the analog to
distributed cognition and collective
intelligence right it's a great question
the first thing that came to mind was
that something like a properly
functioning religion yeah trying my best
not to buy away so I throw in one one
word here that I got from Nora Bateson
which came to mind you're talking he
talked about warm data versus cold data
is that what you're talking about like
warm data would be data that's embodied
in well I mean III got to talk to Nora
directly about this there's a video on
my channel about that conversation
actually with tempte modeling and I
think any Nora means she means she's not
dismissing the effect but she's trying
to point out that we're all always if
you'll allow me this ethnographically
immersed and in the problems that really
matter to us they're not just sort of
problems out there there's there's we
are a complexity there a complexity in
their interactions between them is
complex and so we the warm data is data
that is much more contextually sensitive
and comprehensive and more much more
dynamically sensitive and responsive to
that reality that's how I understood
what she meant by warm data
I don't think the effect part is being
excluded but I think I don't want to say
that that's what she's primarily put her
in your finger on I think she's trying
to put a finger on yeah well no no there
you know there's the kind of data that
we are gathering when we're trying to do
the really important decisions the
decisions that involve commitment that's
essential commitment and transformation
are warm data decisions they're never
data we can never get data that is
coldly dis identified coldly abstracted
and coldly separate from us when we're
trying to wrestle on really important
decisions time that's how I understood
her to mean that okay well sorry Mike
Chris John's question I just threw that
but but three seconds but I think that
idea of one data is exactly the kind of
data processing if you'll allow me to
stretch your metaphor that goes on in
religion so I don't think it's
irrelevant what you said Andrew I don't
think it's great yeah that's very
interesting yeah I'm out that's what
times you get Nagle's with the view from
nowhere right like this is the idea that
actually no it's not science it's
scientists there everyone has a body and
has a family and mother who brought him
forth screaming and the dinner they go
to the bathroom and so the idea that the
scientist is primary that the science
follows from the scientists and you can
take that too far into the postmodern
critique we're all science becomes power
and psychoanalyze away truth and to Bob
you know biography but there is
something really profound about this
reorientation which has happened I think
since the maybe the 90s it's never been
completed that's not well distributed
but there's been an awareness of our
scholars that actually we need to take
the human element within the knowing
system very seriously and that reduces
us down not reduces us but it it shifts
the figure in ground so that we become
aware we become more aware of the kind
of
emotional identity positions that were M
as researchers and and and intellectuals
and things of that nature and yeah and
so in that sense it's similar to
admitting that there are religious
aspects to even science right that we
are investigating truth together and
that if we do it in an earnest enough
manner know that we would end up finding
things that we would kind of live by and
that would allow us as a group to then
do the kind of concern to sermon you're
talking about John like at the cultural
level there have to be these shared
frameworks of value and identity and for
shared frameworks of reality and so
that's interesting and we've you know
that cuts both ways right we know them
bad stories of religion and we know my
why modernity decided to try a different
way of organizing people and it was
important human evasions right right Zak
right it's not like you're not yeah when
you brought up you brought up the
analogy and say well what's that is for
the collective intelligence is a
well-functioning religion all right then
and I want to link it to your previous
point I mean there's there's stuff we
shouldn't unlearned the fact that you're
prepared you if I can put it this way
you're not proposing religion in a
nostalgic fashion you're not saying I
want to give up this is what I mean is
you're doing it right now you're trying
to pull apart right the the invariance
that we should hang on to from religion
if you'll allow me this language and
discern which are the what are the bad
invariants that we need to notice and
let go of so we can break through to a
new developmental stage I think you're
you're doing concretely exactly what I
was asking for yeah and this is the idea
it's a decentering in PHH in terms and
so you're revealing you're moving out
from the surface to the depth and yeah
it's very interesting that notion of
what are the enduring structures that we
need to preserve within the traditions
and what's the form that the enduring
structures take is they're integrated
into new life structures emerge in
structures and so the moment now the
chaotic moment is one where all the
structures are kind of coming undone
which means we can gather the bests
enduring structures together moving
forward yeah so that's that's
interesting frame I like because this
helps to make beautiful to use a phrase
from Plato seven-letter the idea I was
always rendering very in a very ugly
fashion I was trying to talk about
salvaging from these traditions he tries
to find what was what's still good
within which which has been discarded
but I like what how we're talking about
it now I think it's much more refined
and and much more interesting so I guess
so that has something to do with the
living beauty you mentioned beauty right
the living beauty yeah what's what's
there rather than whatever is dogmatic
we're superficial or or dangerous or
that's an excellent that's an excellent
way that's an excellent segue I do
because I mean so if you'll allow me to
talk about a bit you know UDL the the
aesthetics of this are very important
because the aesthetics is precisely
where we're bridging
you know between a lot of these things
would we Karen thing about it when you
when you're experiencing beauty this is
the great photonic inside you're you're
having one of your most profound
cognitive insight but you're also having
an education in the Platonic sense of
you were of your Sensibility and when
you care about right this is why Plato
linked the understanding Beauty to the
cultivation of virtue and so think about
Ron's work on saving beauty and think
about the aesthetics so he he talks
about and you see how this is prescient
along always before all of this hit we
were in what he calls the aesthetics of
the smooth we like things that are
smooth and like objects that are smooth
and we like data production and
communication we want everything to run
smooth
and we want everybody's face and the
smooth is a is an aesthetic that is the
the tyranny of the projection of the
subjective right the world is supposed
to be completely conducive to me and in
no way rupture or challenge me and what
he when he actually says when I think
he's right as he says we've really that
really has lost that aesthetic has
really lost Beauty that's a simulacrum
of beauty rather than beauty itself yeah
which has always has edges to it and and
always is as depth and even isn't a
slightly painful and and well it should
be caring and and yeah yeah exactly
okay describes the angel beauty is a
terror that were basically barely able
and that's so much I think relevant
right now because you know beauty is
something that should I mean it should
strike you that's the verb that Plato
uses repeatedly you're struck by it and
it's and and the Greek is a very violent
striking right and and the point about
the lover and also the fall-off Ilia
Sophia the lover of wisdom is the they
have they have a capacity to do well
these if he has any interest they can
find they can they can accommodate to
the beauty and it's in and they're not
distinguished from each other right the
ability to accommodate the beauty is
precisely what makes it beautiful if you
can't if you can't accommodate you don't
have you don't have ah your terror right
mm-hmm and so this this allows me to
print another question right so think
about the deep interconnection of the
education of sensibility and aesthetics
within a religious community that's
functioning well here's what I think of
you know the work my friend and
colleague Jonathan payaso
where he goes back and he tries to
re-educate people right into what all
this symbolism was doing it you know
aesthetically in this deeper sense that
I'm talking about seeing seeing the the
aesthetics of people's experience as a
fundamental thing sweep okay I'll put it
in a put it in a sentence and I'll turn
it to Zack as a question right I think
you know children go through this the
limo with serious play I've made that
argument before you guys are familiar
with it we can bring it up again
but right I think and coupled to that
has to be an education that removes
aesthetics out of entertainment and puts
it back into education and because
that's part that's a part of is a
religious vision that Zack I think is
alluding to that we have lost the threat
of we've lost the threat of in a
powerful way and so my question to Zack
is that right do you think that so this
is kind of self-deprecating for all of
us as well do you think that the answer
that we're looking for and I don't mean
that as a simple answer you know what I
mean a comprehensive trustworthy
response is going to come out more from
an artistic set of people people that
are at home with the transformative
aspects of beauty then us intellectuals
so I'm getting a lot of emails from
artists now that I didn't I didn't get
before a lot a lot more and they're dirt
they seem to be the people that rush
into the Kairos better than anybody else
because they one of the ways they
systematize the error is if you'll allow
me a verb a they beautify it which isn't
the same thing as resolving it and are
solving it in the intellectual fashion
but they beautify it so that people can
accommodate it and move into it I mean I
think what the answers gotta be of
course of course it's gonna come from
the artists you know I think Plato said
though that often the artist doesn't
know exactly what they're saying on but
they're saying the truth the more
profound truth than the intellectual
could say but they they don't know
exactly what they're saying because
there's an inspiration there's a muse
that
than the inside and so can I just agree
maybe what they know is in the future
they have an insight that is unpacked
that hasn't been unpacked yet so they
have a prophetic as what I wanted is
prophetic yeah that the artist
accredited since which you can't really
access through mere intellectual idea
that the artist is prophetic is I think
it's actually one of the it's kind of
one of the unspoken kind of Gospels of
modernity actually is that the artist is
prophetic the only place where the
Prophet still lives within the kind of
deep disenchanted nature of modernity is
in the artist they get to be the kind of
prophetic voice and Emerson's poet comes
to mind right for Amherst in the poet
was much deeper for Emerson the poet was
like Socrates was the greatest poet
Jesus was the greatest poet right and so
you end up getting this notion that the
artist is exactly the person to live to
and the german idealists ended up here
too with romanticism and and they have
their attempts to create a kind of uber
christianity with all these symbolisms
moved also towards a kind of artist as
social reform on guard and then when you
look at artistic personality types from
a psychological perspective you also see
the sensitives and the people who are
aware of the war in heaven even as the
simulations going and everyone else is
trekked that the world to normal the
artists are usually clued in which is
why I hold artists usually it's actually
kind of a vulnerable population which is
to say they end up medicated or
institutionalized or addicted or
unemployed underemployed miss employed
so there's no Marge marginalize or
systematic the marginalized and
modernity writes that into the artists
that this is well you have to struggle
to mean I justify it but you know other
societies have revered their prophets
although they've been persecuted but so
yeah so I think looking to the aesthetic
and realizing that although we can see
the intellectual synthesis clearly the
way for it to grab
in the human heart is going to come from
something more like an artistic movement
and when you're thinking of the the move
I think of from entertainment to culture
right I think of the theater and I think
of the disappearance of the theater into
the movie right now the potency and the
possibility of the movie to do what the
theater did for ancient Greece right and
to show us this complex cathartic
beautiful thing that allows us to be
people in a new way together like the
film could do that
but I've seen one that's time happy what
I see is mostly an industry which is
capturing attention and etc etc so yes
part of this move out of entertainment
and into culture is changing the
incentive systems around cultural
production and so that means moving the
artists out of marginal into something
like supported right and through either
federal or private reinvestment there's
a serious thinking now in this time of
crisis but a whole bunch of money's
moving around for better and for worse
thinking about what the hell's gonna
happen of the artists right what the
hell is gonna happen to the to the young
yeah the yeah the people who would give
us those symbols and the effective
grounding point so we can move around
the answer that's kind of what's coming
up when I'm thinking about what you said
John and I'm agreeing with you enough to
say whoa yeah we actually get track that
as priority and figure out in schools
and colleges and cities how we can
support artists now it's interesting
problem this this this connects to a lot
of the things that I actually wanted to
talk to you guys about and both both of
you have been talking about stealing the
culture I think that was John's phrase
and your phrase Zak was in your talk you
talked about being an outlaw right and
being an outlaw not in some kind of
let's say
immature adolescent you know
rule-breaking sense but being an outlaw
and as the person who breaks the rules
so that the new rule can emerge or the
new culture can emerge and maybe that's
related somehow to this prophetic artist
personally we're talking about Socrates
was eventually killed by the state and
so I think that's relevant and the
prophets no prophet what did Jesus say
no prophet is honored in his own home
what I'm interested in it may mean
answering that question are people like
Socrates and especially Plato but also
Platonist and people like Barfield and
you know courage and the the early post
content that Zack was alluding to and
Goethe comes to mind as well mom these
are the individuals right and it was
interesting that when Nietzsche
pronounced he gave one clear example
that he stood behind as an example of
the uber mention it wasn't Napoleon that
wasn't Hegel it was good the artist was
good too but but the thing about Goethe
and the thing about Socrates right is
you you baby
let's do at least Plato because Plato
said that he made Socrates more
beautiful let's take Plato because the
the the if you'll allow me the artistry
and the argumentation are completely
interpenetrating so the artistry and the
argumentation and the aspiration are all
deeply interwoven together like you
can't pull them apart like people you
know I
Zack probably had this too maybe you did
Andrew in my education when they taught
me Plato I was taught a great disservice
because what was they would do is they
would distract the arguments out of the
drama
remember the your reference to the
theaters not it was right and they would
and they would not even bringing up it
was it was marginalized to obscurity the
aspiration all right so the artistry and
the aspiration were put aside dismissed
and then always held out is the
argumentation but I'm interested in
those kinds of people who can do it
because I think they
I think they're well I suspect I'm
trying to be very cautious it I suspect
that they're more important than just
the artists right now I think the
aesthetic is important and the artists
are going to be do a lot for us but I
think that the those individuals who
make great art while also making new
forms of thought and new ways of being
that so the three together I think
they're the individuals and what's
interesting for me is I've been trying
to pick up on how do they communicate
and how do they think with and through
other people right
the idea that dialectic is always this
deeply interpenetration of argumentation
aspiration and artistry and in which the
beauty and the truth seek this the
beauty seeking and the truth seeking and
the transformation seeking are all bound
up together and so I'm kind of looking
to see and so here's another hard
question for you is that because you've
been doing really well and answering
them there no but I can make it concrete
how do how do we educate for a good and
this is the question of building which
is of course sourced and that goes back
when I had a conversation with him
recently and he pointed to the whole
building movement and this so this is
important because it's not you toefl the
Builder movement is intubated in
instituted in the secular monastery
retreats retreats that network in the
Scandinavian countries to turn them from
an authoritarian or grand societies into
some of the best most advanced and
happiest places on the earth so this is
not fantasy this is not utopia this is
doable it has been done there's a
historical piece and Thomas book the
Nord a secret lays it out really really
well
yeah and Goethe and Humboldt and they
gather the immediate post Conti in
milieu it was that sense of and you're
right to correct me there that it's the
it's all three it's the good deterrent
beautifully United and so complex symbol
right and that in our society someone
who's capable of doing that probably
looks more like an artist
scientists as Girja did right but as
many people know correct it was actually
a totally badass scientist and this was
real rough Steiners many people don't
know this Rudolf Steiners first work was
actually in the archives of Goethe
looking at his scientific work and so
there's a richness there but yeah so the
point being that yeah the what we're
looking for is that complex truly after
modern right to the the differentiation
of the value spheres separating art from
science from morality right the idea
that they need to be reintegrated in
some new form that's the that's the in a
sense the holy grail of of the of the
West that the only way out of this is
the somehow reintegrate these these
values spheres and to somehow find forms
of expression and communication and
interaction that represent a new merger
of them not a regression back to the
medieval system where they refused
together right where you couldn't get
that's their work because there's so
many you can't talk about the planets
because we already know because there's
so many orifices in this face that there
can't be some of it so like the dogmatic
don't look through the telescope Galileo
pre-modern undifferentiated than the
differentiated modernity and then Weber
lays out the problem right the
technocrats without heart and the
aesthetic artists without any sense of
ethics and the fragmentation of the
unity dimensional man and so always the
quest has been there's free integration
and one way to think about the problem
is actually also as a there's a
socio-economic thing here that in fact
we need to heal certain underlying
social structures to allow for those
forms of complex identity formation back
to the question of Education which is
where you're moving this because the
caricature of the artist right now is
some wounded degenerate tight who's kind
of an egomaniac and doesn't get along
with the rest of society and
narcissistic and and the scientists and
the scientists the and he's got no
emotions and he might as well be a robot
right and the politician is cutthroat
and the businessman has no morals or
aesthetic sense and so that
sense that there's each person with this
fragmented so can I say that maybe the
artist is actually the total person
right it's not it's not being an artist
as a specialized activity in a sense
being an artist is is what we're all
sort of the total person meant to be on
some level right whether you actually
art or not if we're using artists in
that sense that we were where the artist
is the one who finds a way to make a
life that reunites the fragmented value
spheres of modernity right that that
like I said the Emersonian poet who
integrates the good the true and the
beautiful if that's the artist talking
about then yes but again the the artist
of modernity right the mad genius like
derelict marginalized artists is as much
of a kind of character as the modern
businessman or the modern politician yes
also stopped from having aesthetic sense
or an ethical sense and so it's it's
just that sense again the whole person
where you can essentially not be
fragmented at such a root level
alongside clefts and identity as the
good determine the beautiful and I get
the sense that like when we were talking
the other day I mentioned poetry and
John kind of jumped and said no because
of the way people think of a poet today
it's there's this contempt for poetry
right and then maybe this event that's
happening right now when people are
stuck in their houses etc etc maybe they
will start to see a little bit like the
value of that from the poetic poetry are
oh I agree I think that crisis it does
two things and they play off against
each other I mean it creates Dom aside
it because people connection it brings
on loneliness it puts them into this
weird and threatening you know almost
demonic you know world view and so in
many ways and we're already seeing this
it exacerbates the meaning crisis I
predict we're going to see a mental
health crisis
shortly on the heels of this that is
going to also be Titanic and caused a
suffering and death but Pressley because
of that people are right also turning to
seeing how important meaning making is
not semantic meaning talking about
meaning in life meaning making the
connectedness but I want to I want to I
want to bring up so I think you're right
that that's part of the car Ross Andru
but I want to say that I think the
Kairos and our discussion is leading me
to the deeper question so that keeps
giving these great answers and then I
can they afford me going deeper and this
may be you know cycles back to Tillich
and maybe he cycles back to the good in
variants and the bad in variants because
whatever what I wanted to say think
about how we got here so I'm using
hammer Mouse here think about how God
separated those three faculties in the
three critiques deterioration judgment
frightened practically separate right he
separates them and then Harbor of
Martha's argument is part of what drives
that fragmentation is a normativity of
autonomy reason is autonomous and
therefore it cannot and should not be
integrated or reduced it's in a sense
even in commensurable from right from
morality which is then also autonomous
the right is a tournament and that's
autonomous from taste
so the normativity of autonomy right arm
is for grounded and that is you feel
large or no that's an autonomy and maybe
Heidegger and my colleague of mine
Johannes Nina Hauser that that's that's
a normativity ultimately of subjectivity
self-governing autonomous right right
right it's it's ultimately a Cartesian
normativity yeah no I I am ultimately an
isolated right thing and itself and and
my north and the only normativity upon
me is my
my autonomy and all of these do you see
what I'm trying to get out there's a
normativity of autonomy now
Tillich in his work tried to break out
of that he tried to say there's three
possible kinds of normativity there's of
course the normativity of autonomy and
that's is pervasive in the cognitive
grammar of modernity and then he said
but there's also of course the
normativity I called it heteronomy in
which somebody is imposing on us and
this is a this is an authoritarian of
one form of another and he was he was
brilliant enough to see how the Nazis
were playing those two off against each
other when they I don't want to bring up
the Nazis very key it this this analysis
afforded him insight and then he
proposed you'll see where I'm going with
this
you posts he those two he said what we
really need because the first emphasizes
subjectivity right autonomy the second
got localizes everything in objectivity
right but he said there's a third which
is the enemy and this is being god
governed right and and this brings us
back again to the well-functioning
religion the idea is there are a certain
form because when people feel called by
God they don't feel that they're being
demonically possessed but they don't
feel like they're acting autonomously
they feel it's if they feel
simultaneously that they are moving
they're being moved by something beyond
themselves but they're also being moved
by something that is helping them to
realize themselves in an important way
and so I think part I think there's a
deep reason by and to why you brought
this up and I think it's even a deep
fear since a while you circle back the
well-functioning religion like if we're
going to break out of the fragmentation
we have to challenge the normativity
that drives the fragmentation which is
the absolute value radiation of autonomy
as the final way in which all
normativity is generated no that's not
to give in to hitter on me and say
what we need is the strong man and the
authoritarian structure and Tillich was
really playing with the idea that what
Christianity was trying to offer people
was the Animus um normativity and it
would break us out and we help to
reunite us as an entire person
well that's very abstract and so that's
exactly what Zak was talking about when
when you talk about the unique self
Symphony I have it written down here in
a mystical body of Christ it's breaking
out modern idea of self right our modern
idea of self into something else you
call that sovereign self I'm not quite
sure I understand what I want to reform
I think that's what the back was that's
exactly Zacks yes concept and he also
you're also said that's the mystical
body of Christ right yes yeah right
that's not that's not the most
conventional way in but yes eventually
is in one consistent mystical body of
Christ and it was interesting here so we
can go back to the developmental theory
because that stack you just ran from
heteronomous to autonomous - what was
its feel the Ottomans Fionna Fionna miss
Wright which you could also think of
theosis becoming more public yeah and so
that that stacks very closely to the pre
conventional conventional post
conventional way of thinking about moral
development which is of course inspired
by count through Kohlberg and picked up
by Hamas as part of our bosses moral and
political theory and when you look at
how must fear of democracy is actually
trying to overcome the autonomously
bastes rationality of the subject of
modernity and get in its place not a
Christianity based notion of
post-convention alibiing but a post
conventionality nonetheless and so you
end up having a way of thinking about
moral development where the higher
reaches you get a a transcending of the
modern autonomous
kind of like subject and a relinquishing
into community and also into
transcendence people in realized
Kohlberg had a famous comer had a famous
7th level like he had a sixth stage
model for his whole career but he ended
up in a essay writing about this 7th
stage in the seventh stage the exemplars
were like Spinoza and Socrates and he
leered a shard on and Marcus Aurelius
and people who got all the way up to the
post conventional autonomy that one
would expect and then also gave over the
self and that kind of Abraham has those
self-transcending kind of giving over
the self on the altar of the ideal and
and so that yeah that's a different form
of identity which allows for a different
kind of politics and a different kind of
art and science and and everything but
the task demands of that are quite steep
and this is like one of the flaws and
harbor mosses feared democracy between
facts and norms is this big thick book
and the issue there is that he's
expecting all citizens to be able to be
post conventional in their moral
judgment and this is very I mean this is
where then you know Dewey comes in right
that education democracy are like this
that if you going to have a kind of
decentralized
sense making as a way of running it if
you really want to do that then you need
get everyone up through the educational
system to a very very high level of
complexity and identity formation yes so
we were at this notion that there's yet
pre conventional conventional
postconventional that the challenging
basis of the the root of the modern form
of normativity basically is what we were
looking at and it has to do also
challenging the route of the modern
identity so the new form of new form of
normativity a new form of self Co emerge
Robert Brandon who's one of the great
philosophers of our time University
incredible work on the nature of
normativity and actually rehearsing
Hegel in a profound way is this great
section heading for his win one it was
his big book making explicit it says we
have met the norms and they are ours and
this is just to say that you know one of
the things that makes the post
conventional identity post conventional
is that they're norming the norms that
the practice is they're not disobeying
the norms we're not even understanding
the norms but understanding the norms
and then getting above them and being
able to norm the norms but norm the
norms in by virtue of what and now we're
back to the discernment and the Congress
right which is that you if you go post
conventional there's this delicate
moment and Kohlberg research which is
that you've critiqued the norms of
society but you haven't established a
principled view of your own so now your
supervening on the norms of society
critiquing everything turning into a
relativist and the hedonist which is
what happened a lot in these transitions
and you haven't got found a discourse
community of other post commencement
people that will allow you to
equilibrate in a in principled way and
have a sovereign and a sovereign notion
or wave forward and so yeah so that's
funny educational challenges you can
only be a heretic if you found other
heretics or people yeah and this is the
dialogue oops we're developing another
trends your trends your transcending
that the norms and bring it to a higher
level and moving between communication
communities so moving between identity
structures is often involves moving
between communication communities and
expanding your communication community
often to include the mighty dead right
like that you don't have a local
community where you can talk at the way
you need to talk to be who you are you
need to expand and have conversations
with more and more and one of the ways
to ground post conventional morality
which is to say I'm not appealing to my
community about what's right and wrong
rather I'm appealing to what George
Herbert Mead called an ideal
communication community this is back to
the yellow he write that there's a
community in which I am a part of which
is not spatio-temporal located by which
I judge my behavior so it's not you guys
local community to which I'm beholden no
though I am because you're my immediate
neighbors but I'm holding to this ideal
communication community which could be
all sentient beings if you wanted to be
so there's something there too about how
to create context we're post-convention
identities can be formed through
conversation and linked into the ideal
communication communities beyond the
loved goal to have that sense of courage
and ancestry and all the things that
constitute identity which are hard to
come by if you're trapped in a local
conventional community and that won't
allow for your identity formation and so
much possibility of identity formation
has been opened up with a move atom
journeying to post leader nians digital
but we still haven't solidified the dye
logos of actual identity construction at
the post commencement level we're mostly
critiquing and outside of the norms
without having any way to norm the norms
with systemic conversation and so we're
back at post conventional religion again
or we're back at what some conventional
religion but we're also and I think
we're also into the circling back to
Piaget I think we're going to post
formal thought where we're not we don't
just think within an axiomatic system we
learn how to think between axiomatic
systems and that's each one of these
that each one of these normativity sees
itself as an axiomatic system but we
have to remember we've got we've got you
know a really profound truth that
undermines that which is no system is
simultaneously complete and consistent
go to the every system has to have a
doorway out of it and you can't infer a
stronger language or a stronger logic
from the weaker logic etc all these
things that have told us that the that
that if our claims to autonomy are
ultimately not viable because that
autonomy can never have a complete
normativity because it will always trade
between consistency and completeness if
it tries to pursue Venus you will start
to give up and its consistency and then
that make that destabilizes it or if it
tries to remain consistent it then
freezes so it's these systems are always
always hovering between destabilization
and fixation and so that for me gives me
great hope but what and I like the
invocation of the logos right diello
goes the way of the logos the logo says
that thing that's norming the norms I
like the way you put that sorry and what
I want to bring in it and this comes
from Tillich but it is ultimately due to
Heidegger is and it goes to both
Maslow's and on Kohlberg
self-transcendence right to think about
the logos is it has the life of its own
it's not it's not and it's not
abstractly independent from us but it's
right it doesn't belong to us we belong
to it it takes on a life of its own and
here's the thing and not only it not
only right it is not only connected to
us it's also connected to the way
intelligibility and even reality are
unfolding and that that's ultimately I
think why we belong to it rather than it
belonging to us and so part of what I
think the sage artists can do is in is
invoke do logos and invoke that as you
know the thing the the sort of trans
systemic thing that allows us to bridge
between the normativity is an important
way and I think the so I want to throw
in that one of the things that has
supported the autonomy and the
subjectivity you know model and and then
and then we have this thing called
authenticity which isn't part of your
sense it just basically means sort of
celebrating your autonomy right um but
one of one of the one of the things that
I'm trying to get at
right is this idea that in the dialogue
and in the dialectic we have access to
right a way like when you when you read
when you read the dialogues it's not
just argumentation that's in competition
ways of life are being brought into
competition but not just in an arbitrary
fashion they're being regulated but is
that's the right word there being
regulated by the logos and everybody has
to be willing to follow the logos which
doesn't mean just drifting subjectively
it means you know answering the call
being responsive to the way it's taken
on a life of its own and then it's it's
polarity is it's not grounded in us it's
grounded between us and each other and
the end our culture of intelligibility
and ultimately the world in which that
culture is embedded like the logos the
logos exemplifies the normativity of our
embeddedness Animax it for us and I
think that is a way in which linked with
sort of post conventional thinking it
can help us to get the kind of Fionna
--mess normativity that I'm trying to
talk about the you know well we talked
about this and Zack Zack because you use
it's there's something sacred or perhaps
even divine about the logos that and
that's what I'm trying to get it to take
the role the Fionna the Fiona might roll
that till it was 22 words
did that make sense I was struggling
that what I did know I mean it was it's
a beautiful international essentially
what I'm hearing is that this artists
we've been talking about this like
Gertie and RDS who integrates the value
spheres what they're creating their
words like they're they're inviting us
actually to something into sometimes
ritual some kind of ritual of
interaction and communication where the
logos is revealed between us
right yeah the artist needs to create
our collective yeah form it's like a
perform that's why Theatre is so
interesting and a theater that would
break down that fourth wall and engage
the audience you know and so they're
always hints in postmodern art that
there was something trying to emerge
that would actually embrace the audience
and blur the line between the art and
non-art though and essentially Rhys ACK
realized all of life by casting the veil
of art across all things and so that
notion that the artists were looking for
someone who invites us into a new ritual
and way of being worth through it we
can't help but be swept into the logo
he's essentially and that were going
full circle into the logos mysticism
right of the the Western tradition
rooted in the Neoplatonic stuff and yet
a sense that there's a way to there's a
way to create a human civilization so
I'm thinking of the tightness here in
particular he he almost built a city yes
big novel is it yeah exactly he must
build the city and so he was in this
kind of civilizational design mindset
from a deeply meta philosophical the a
platonic video and to my sense is that
yeah in this such a society there would
be some kind of and again when you think
of properly functioning religion it's
not just like the books and stuff right
it's like there's a building and we all
get there and we're in it together and
we do something and what that something
is is a ritual that would be
tremendously beautiful and that would
then the conception of it would be as
you're describing John it would be not
us all looking at one thing like some
medieval ritual but in fact this moving
between us of the Holy Spirit and of the
dialogue goes yeah where the evidence is
clear just by that were fact we're here
together looking one other's eyes and
that's what can happen sometimes that's
why a a works and that's why circling
works a bunch of other things work
because you just it descends it's there
you're looking between the eyes there's
a self-evident how
in the experience personhood and
co-relating and it's funny it's like
they always say you're selling water by
the well or selling water by the river
or something like that I think this is
one of those things you know and that
it's right there and I like the idea
that the logos is building something
like you said building a city or a
Patronus is building a city that strikes
me as that's the thing that is building
the city of God is the logos or you know
if we got yeah incredible terms there's
two myths to identification crisis
identified with the body of the church
but Christ is also identified with the
logos of God right and it's because I
said because he media's between them and
he creates ways of being
he was the followers of Christianity
were the followers of Jesus were
originally not called Christians that
was an insult they originally called
themselves followers of the way right
followers of the way yeah this way of
being exemplified rendered beautiful to
us attracts us it's proleptic it
inspires us to ask fire it affords
appreciation right it allows us to be
you know a postformal allows us to be
postconventional you know it's famous
augustine you know you know learn how to
love God and then do whatever you want
that the to be right that the two are
always bound together
that's faith again that's something to
do with faith isn't it well following
the logos you're following faith in a
way you're not following a kind of you
don't have a model it's not how to build
the thing you're following a third
element you are it depends on your
definition faith like circling or in a a
meeting or even these conversations here
yeah like I came into the conversation
with a certain they thought it was going
to be a good conversation I had no idea
exactly how it's going to go but I knew
given the nature of reality and my
experience with all you guys that there
was a sense that it was going
work I don't know exactly how this is
like a micro example it's not it's not
like a deep faith but there's a sense
that reality holds together and so
similarly when you're with people in one
of these situations were the logos
emergence that's what I mean by faith
reality holding together or something
reality holds together that there's a
and that we're intimate with reality
that it's not absent from our perception
and so the faith read the reality of
other people for example is what it
emerges when you're gonna dialogue us
that if we trust the conversation and
trust reason in our better lights and
the care we have for one another that
we'll find the solution and so it's a
faith in humanity needs you're certain
which then and then I can extend
different notes that everything's gonna
work out and be fine different for the
faith that one won't go to heaven and it
requires time too it requires an
unfolding of time it can't just be
rushed or constructed right I'm covering
becoming back to Kairos yeah yeah I
wanted to say how much Zach said I think
he hears again what we're doing serving
we're pulling again we're pulling apart
two notions of faith right there's a one
that was grounded in sort of you know
the emergence of subjectivity which is
the assertion right be a willful
assertion against evidence which has
become a primitive model whereas men of
faith that Zak is talking about and I'm
talking about tune especially some of
the conversations I'm having with Jordan
Hall is this sense you know of
continuity of contact and you're not
trying to come to closure what you're
trying to do is always educate right
relationship right relationship isn't a
gold state it's like Keeks does great
work on this he says don't confuse goals
with ideals and I and we even misused
the word ideal he said he complained you
know there's a bull state I'm hungry and
I don't want to be hungry so I can get
to a state that realizes and then I can
rest there right there is
ideals are not states of completion and
finality in which you rest satisfied my
ideals are constant right
well there
they're there more there their
constraints on the manner of how you do
it but honesty isn't a place I'm trying
to get to I can now say okay I'm done
with honesty I don't need honesty I'm
finished
all right I'm complete honesty isn't
instead it's an ideal it's a whole it's
a way of being in right relationship
with yourself and other people in an
ongoing fashion yeah so there's any
completeness to right it's never
completed right
you know like sorry and this just comes
to my mind like Moses never gets to the
the promised land and John the Baptist
has to die before you know it's like
we're all sort of like we're doing
something on faith because it will never
realize that final construction or
that's why don't perfection right right
that's right and but ultimately we're
which find the faith is always affording
the emergence precisely because it's
only in the logos of emergence that we
move into post conventionality that we
can be postformal
that we can find the resources to
respond to Kairos it's also that that
the you can't write you can't make it a
goal okay you know 20 minutes in logos
is going to appear in the conversation
that's not gonna happen
that's not gonna happen in fact taking
that stance will kill it right will kill
it completely well it won't show up it
won't show up sorry Zach you wanted to
say something no I mean I'm I'm really
vibing on it and I'm thinking with the
ideal notion and I'm thinking of Tillich
- in the his notion of idolatry right
just yeah you invest something with
infinite worth it's not actually
infinite and the proper ideal would be
infinite that you precisely couldn't
achieve it in this life and that's why
you've adopted it as your ideal on some
of the most compelling religious ideals
have that quality like Buddhahood for
example like media which contains a
whole bunch of qualities that you're
unlikely to achieve in this lifetime but
wish you were strong right again even
the love of wisdom for luck finally Oh
Sophia you are always in love with
wisdom because you would never be a God
you would never be perfectly wise right
yeah exactly answer that that it is
infinitely pursuable like asymptotic
throughout life basically it's the
notion of the of the ideal which is you
know very different from other ways of
having motivation and so the question of
the how the post conventional identity
is ideal driven where has many forms of
conventional identity or goal driven is
an important statement and as we know
for most of the happiness research
actually when you meet your goal watch
out because that's when the depression
sets and often people winning gold
medals and and super bowls and then get
suicidal afterwards because they
actually did it whereas the ideal is
actually infinitely renewable like
resource of identity construction you
know right it if it in finite game it
right yeah courses you know that follows
up on his previous book the religious
case against belief and you know playing
a finite game versus playing an infinite
game and I think playing in a sense of
serious play like playing a musical
instrument rather than fooling around or
yeah yeah or jazz where you jazz is a
post formal post conventional thing it
you can't do jazz unless you've done you
have to go through that whole
developmental education or you can't do
it same thing with Tai Chi if you spend
a lot of time getting the form before
you actually start to get the Chi which
is normal which is behind the form yeah
I'd have to go soon guys I've already
delayed another meeting a bit but well I
think I I like what we got to and I'd
like to continue on with but we were
doing a lot of this in we were
exemplifying what I was the discernment
we were trying to get out separating the
good invariants from the bottom various
the wheat from the shaft right and and
and and then how do we educate for that
I think this is the question I would
like to return to with the two of you
guys again please
yeah I always feel this is very
unfinished every time we we do this I
feel like it's because it just keeps
going and going
there's just like I've asked I've only
asked about two of the ten questions
that I was thinking of no yeah no I'm
asking you guys so so I'd be you know
I'd be thrilled to take to keep it going
well I propose we can take we try to
pick up the threads here and we also try
and answer more of your questions Andrew
because I think they will they will
afford more good discussion okay I agree
thanks thanks so much thank you it's
always good someday we will meet in
person that would be really wonderful
okay great